We'll call for some questions and comments after that. So on we go.
Sounds good. Okay.
I'm Lindsay Gibson.
Kia ora. Do you
want
to introduce yourselves?
Sure.
Rachel Patrick
Jason Hewitt
Kia
ora.
Thanks,
Lindsay.
So as you know, we've given you written advice already.
Excuse my voice, I've been a little bit sick.
Yeah.
We've given you written advice already on the report.
We felt that given we've only got half an hour, it'd be good for you to just throw
any questions you might have our way, and then at the end of the session,
maybe we just give you some suggested areas of next steps for this.
Lindsay, I know you're considering your advice to next
iteration of yourselves.
Exactly.
And so we felt that the best way to bring
value from the report would be in terms of what you might want to suggest for that
next committee to do with the recommendations from the report.
Yeah.
And I think that's where the focus needs to be, is we as a committee and
our ability to conduct inquiry,
briefings, reports, et cetera-
Yeah
... to better the outcome of what we're trying to seek here, in the
recommendations and that there. And that was the
basis of my first line of questioning was is,
Lindsay, you've been working with this committee for quite some time, is,
number one, we need to be informed.
Right. Yeah.
This report goes some way.
Mm-hmm.
And you know that we did make some visits over this term out and
about just to see how Māori out
on the whenua, how they actually feel the Crown is going in all
its different responsibilities, if we call it that.
Mm-hmm.
And I think probably one of the areas that drew out to me in the report was
about the relationships,
which is more than just transactional.
And maybe we start with that then and turn that into a question is
where the office feels the challenges that we
have as a government with relationships, because I'd imagine it's very much
department to department, ministry, where our
challenges are. Because I feel that for us to be effective as a
committee, we would love to hold government to account.
Now that's a very general sense as a title.
But to potentially bring some of the areas that we're challenged with-
Mm-hmm
... and bring them here-
... to be able to ask some questions and say, "Well,
how can we help you?"
Ken.
Space
really in terms of the accountability for
outcomes and how it's obviously system wide and
system leaders and the role that they have, but also
understanding that each agency department has a
very different role in what they're trying to deliver.
And I think one of the things that's really come out of this report is it
has to be quite tailored in understanding, okay, what are
we trying to achieve as an agency, and how do we
tailor how we work with Māori in terms of that, but also there's
this 360 degree piece, isn't there, in terms of understanding
on,
at the grassroots level, how is that
response being met? How is it being interpreted?
How is that relationship really being built and
go with. But I'll let Rachel speak to that a little bit.